Albert Gallatin Marchand Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Albert Gallatin Marchand Papers 1801-1862 1839-1843
MSS86302
Marchand, Albert Gallatin, 1811-1848
250 items
3 containers
1 linear foot
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
United States representative and lawyer. Correspondence, a speech, and a printing plate relating chiefly to Marchand's two terms in the United States House of Representatives and life in Washington, D.C.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Kuhns, Daniel S., 1818 or 1819- --Correspondence.; Marchand, Albert Gallatin, 1811-1848.; Marchand, Susan S., 1820-1896--Correspondence.; Tyler, John, 1790-1862.; Van Buren, Martin, 1782-1862.
Organizations
Democratic Party (U.S.); Gadsby's Hotel (Washington, D.C.); United States. Congress.; United States. Congress. House.; Whig Party (U.S.)
Subjects
Independent treasury.; Legislators--United States.; Political parties--United States.
Places
Capitol Hill (Washington, D.C.); Pennsylvania--Politics and government--1775-1865.; United States--Politics and government--1815-1861.; Washington (D.C.)--Social life and customs.
Occupations
Lawyers.; Representatives, U.S. Congress--Pennsylvania.
Provenance
The papers of Albert Gallatin Marchand were given to the Library of Congress by Amanda Sutphin in 2019.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Albert Gallatin Marchand are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1811, Feb. 27 Born, near Greensburg, Pa.
1833 Admitted to the Pennsylvania state bar and opened law practice
1839 Married Susan S. Kuhns (died 1896)
1839 1843 Member, United States House of Representatives
1840 Birth of son, William K. Marchand (died 1862)
1840 1841 Member, House Committee on Accounts
1841 Birth of son, John A. Marchand (died 1896) Birth of daughter, Kate Marchand (died 1936)
1842 Declined renomination to Congress
1843 Returned to Greensburg, Pa., and resumed law practice
1845 Birth of daughter, Lizzie Marchand (died 1936)
1848, Feb. 5 Died, Greensburg, Pa.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Albert Gallatin Marchand span the period 1801-1862, with the bulk of the material dating from 1839 to 1843. The collection documents Marchand’s tenure as a two-term Democratic member of the United States House of Representatives (1839-1843) and his life as a transitory resident of Washington, D.C., and consists almost entirely of letters to his wife, Susan S. (Kuhns) Marchand. Though he was not an influential member of the House, Marchand's correspondence provides insight into the daily workings of that body during the administrations of presidents Martin Van Buren and John Tyler. (No letters from William Henry Harrison’s month-long presidency are included.) He offers observations on the legislative process, comments on the distinctions between Democrats and Whigs, and relates his often witty and withering assessments of fellow representatives. His letters convey the details of his daily routine, such as living arrangements at Gadsby’s Hotel and other temporary residences and his frequent constitutionals around Capitol Hill, while also expressing his longing to return home to his wife and young children. Additional correspondence includes letters from Susan’s brother, Daniel S. Kuhns, a letter from Marchand to his younger brother, Henry Clay Marchand, and an 1862 condolence letter to Susan upon the death of William K. Marchand, Albert and Susan’s son. Of note is his June 8, 1840, speech supporting the creation of an independent United States treasury, the collection's sole item of an official nature illustrating his role as a representative.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Container List
- Family correspondence (Box 1)
  - Brownson, James I., 1862 (Box 1)
  - Kuhns, Daniel S., 1842 (Box 1)
  - Marchand, Albert Gallatin (Box 1)
    - 1839, Jan.-1840, May, (11 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1840, June-1842, June, (10 folders) (Box 2)
    - 1842, July-1843, Aug., (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Treseler, Emanuel, 1801 (Box 3)
- Printing plate for calling card, undated (Box 3)
- Speech, 1840, June 8 (Box 3)